Finding Aid for the Lloyd E. Cotsen Cuneiform Tablets Collection LSC.1883
UCLA Library Special Collections
Lloyd E. Cotsen cuneiform tablets collection
circa 3200-1500 BCE
UCLA Library Special Collections
Cotsen, Lloyd E.
LSC.1883
20.6 Linear Feet (206 custom boxes)
The collection consists of 215 cuneiform tablets, the majority of which were written by students in ancient Mesopotamian schools. Tablet subjects include writing composition and language, mathematics, science, law, and religion. The chronological range of the tablets extends from the Uruk Period (c. 3200 BCE) to the Old Babylonian period (c. 1800-1600 BCE).
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Cotsen Family Foundation, gift, 2011.
Custodial History
The Lloyd Cotsen cuneiform tablets collection was created from smaller, private collections, acquired over several decades. The tablets in the Cotsen Collection were chosen specifically for their scholastic content. The tablets were integrated into the Cotsen Children's Library Collection housed at Princeton University. In 2011 the Cotsen Institute donated the cuneiform tablet section of the Children's Library to UCLA Special Collections.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9971042013606533
Biographical / Historical
Lloyd E. Cotsen (1929-2017) was a former chief executive officer and chairman of the board of Neutrogena Corporation. Cotsen earned a bachelor's degree in History from Princeton University (1950), served in Navy during the Korean War, and received an MBA from Harvard Business School (1957). He was an avid collector of materials related to folk art, children's literature, and archeology, and accumulated vast collections of Japanese baskets, textiles, children's books, and Chinese mirrors. Over his lifetime he donated portions of his collections to a varity of insitutions, including San Fransico's Asian Art Museum, Princeton Univeristy, and the Museum of International Folk Art in Santa Fe, New Mexico. In 2000 UCLA renamed its Institute of Archaeology the Cotsen Institute of Archaeology.
Scope and Content
This collection provides a comprehensive view of scribal training and writing techniques in the Mesopotamian educational system covering a span of 1600 years. The collection consists of 215 cuneiform tablets (211 school texts and four non-school texts) from Mesopotamia (ancient Iraq). These tablets were written in the Mesopotamian school, the eduba ("House of Tablets"), by students training to become professional scribes, dubsar ("tablet writer").
The majority of tablets in this collection date to the Old Babylonian period (c. 1900-1600 BCE), which was known for the development and proliferation of individual scribal schools. In addition to the Old Babylonian texts there are tablets from the Uruk III period (c. 3200-3000 BCE), the Early Dynastic III period (c. 2600-2350 BCE), the Old Akkadian period (c. 2340-2200 BCE), and the Third Dynasty of Ur (c. 2100-2000 BCE).
School texts cover a rich variety of topics, yet comprise a very small percentage of known cuneiform documents. This collection includes exercises in vocabulary, sign formation, literature, grammar, law, epistles, administration, sealing and stylus practices. These student exercises cover the entire curriculum of scribal training, from the most basic beginner lessons to the advanced lessons of the final stage of education. The wide variety of exercise offers researchers unique insight into the everyday life of the ancient Mesopotamian.
Typical for the period and genre, the majority of the school texts are written in Sumerian. A few dozen tablets, mostly letters, are written in Akkadian, while a handful of lexical texts contain multiple languages (Sumerian, Akkadian, West Semitic). It is not clear in the remaining tablets, mostly mathematical exercises, which language is being used by the scribe.
The non-school texts include one legal document from the Early Dynastic period, and three letters written by king Rim-Suen of Larsa (c. 1822-1763 BCE). These royal letters are part of an ancient archive that has since been dispersed across several collections in America and Europe.
Organization and Arrangement
Tablets are arranged and described at the item level.
Digital Images Available
Digital images of tablets from this collection are available electronically at https://cdli.ucla.edu/.
Related Material
Edward A. Dickson Cuneiform Tablet collection (LSC 1813). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Cumberland Clark Cuneiform Tablet Collection (LSC 1826). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Cuneiform tablets.; Sumerian language -- Writing; Akkadian language -- Writing; Scribes -- Iraq -- Babylonia -- History -- Sources; Education -- Iraq -- Babylonia -- History -- Sources; Cotsen, Lloyd E.
- School text, lexical exercise of wooden items., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); 31718.3; 3 3/8" diameter x 1" depth, lentil with erasures; Lenticular tablet that is actively crumbling. The tablet has some deep complete and incomplete cracks on the inscribed face and over portions of the edge. There are other shallower incomplete cracks overall. There are surface losses on the inscribed face that obscure portions of the cuneiform inscriptions. The uninscribed surface is uneven: there are some rough, slightly raised patches of clay as well as some pit-like losses overall. There is a black spot near the edge, as well as some mottled black areas overall. There is some spalling visible on one portion of the edge. (Drawer 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This is a basic vocabulary exercise in writing various types of wooden objects.
- School text, literary exercise from a proverb., Ur III - Old Babylonian Period (c. 2100-1600 BCE); SC-I-8; 1. He slept peacefully among the mountains.; 3 1/4" diameter x 1 3/8" depth, baked lentil; Lenticular tablet with multiple mounds of mineral deposits overall, though located primarily near the edges. The convex face has some minor surface abrasions. (Drawer 2)
  This is an advanced student's exercise in writing an unidentified proverb.
- School text, erased exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-38; (Too broken to reconstruct); 3 3/16" height x 2 1/2" width x 1" depth, rectangular tablet largely effaced; Rectangular tablet with uninscribed face that has a very uneven surface. The inscribed face and edges of the tablet are uneven, but only slightly in comparison to the uninscribed face. There are three long scrapes across the uninscribed face that appear to have been made when the clay was still wet. There are folds and wrinkles in the clay that also appear to have been made when the clay was still wet. There are some other minor surface losses on this face as well as on the rest of the tablet. On the inscribed face, there are two incomplete cracks. There is one pit-like loss on this face, possibly made by an implement. There are also some minor losses to two of the corners.There are some white concretions visible throughout. (Drawer 3)
  This student exercise has been erased.
- School text, mathematical exercise for profit calculation., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-IV-9; 2 1/2" height x 2 5/16" width x 3/4" depth, square single column tablet with an adhesive label; Square tablet that has a deep, complete crack running across the tablet. Much of this crack has been covered and filled with an adhesive. There are a few incomplete cracks that extend from the complete crack. There are a few other minor losses overall. There is a circular white label adhered to one edge inscribed with "1.". (Drawer 4)
  This basic student exercise contains mathematical calculations for ascertaining profit.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 122; (Too fragmentary to reconstruct); 2 3/4" diameter x 1 3/8" depth, misshapen lentil with the reverse inscribed; Lenticular tablet that was partially crushed while the clay was still wet, leaving it misshapen. One face is light orange and the other is milky-tan. The light orange face has two side-by-side scrapes from a modern tool near the edge. A crack runs through one of the scrapes and about half way through the side to the opposite face. Another crack at the opposite end of this face also continues onto a side. There is one complete crack on this face; it runs almost through the middle, but it is a very slender crack. The milky-tan face shows the complete crack just described. On one edge there is a fragile bulging point with a deep crack and two small chips that look like they may dislodge. One fragment has already dislodged and has been placed in the storage bag. From this face, a narrow diagonal scrape is visible on the side; it appears to be made by a modern tool, because it does not have the same patina as the rest of the tablet. (Drawer 5)
  This basic student exercise is practice writing personal names. Due to the surface damage the text is largely illegible.
- School text, sign exercise of the "a" sign., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 66; 1. Water; Square tablet with a small chip and loss at one corner. Close to the diagonally opposite corner there is a small loss, but this loss is more clearly visible on one face than on the other. The tablet does not appear coated. It is lighter in color than many other tablets- it is dark tan rather than orange. (Drawer 6)
  This beginner's exercise is a practice in sign formation and sound. This tablet is a possible fake. The scribe wrote the sign for "water" in irregularly shaped columns and cases, transposing columns on the same face.
- School text, mathemtical exercise of metrology., Ur III - Early Old Babylonian Period (c. 2100-1800 BCE); SC-I-38; 2 7/8" diameter x 3 1/4" depth, hexagonal rounded prism joined from fragments; Cylindrical tablet fragment with an intentional hole running down the center. The fragment has broken into four pieces. The four pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. The adhesive is visible in the breaks and on the surface in some areas around the breaks. There are also a number of crevices and losses, particularly around and by the breaks. There is a small loss that has been reattached in one of the crevices. There are also other losses to the surface. One end of the tablet has groove marks across the surface, most likely made by an implement, possibly to break this fragment apart from another piece. On this same end, there is a deep loss. There are white concretions overall. The fragment is actively crumbling in some places. (Drawer S2)
  This student exercise is practice writing and understanding silver weights comprised of the whole range of metrological units: grains, shekels, minas and talents.
- School text, lexical exercise from the Early Dynastic Word List C., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-36; Obverse Column 1 1. advise 2. … 3. secret 4. purification priest 5. 5 units of salt 6. 5 units of a dairy product 7. 5 units of halub berries 8. 10 ducks 9. 10 male goats 10. 10 … sheep 11. 10 fat-tailed sheep 12. … suckling calves 13. … 14. … (Remaining 4 lines missing) Column 2 1. 4 metal daggers 2. 10 … animals 3. 10 units of milk 4. 1 unit of cream 5. 10 cows 6. 1 … 7. 10 ewes 8. 1 stud 9. 10 … 10. 1 male goat 11. … bird 12. 71 13. a high-ranking official 14. a singer 15. a barber 16. … 17. … (Remaining 2 lines missing) Column 3 1. 5 units of salt 2. 5 units of a dairy product 3. 5 units of halub berries 4. 10 ducks 5. 1 male goat 6. 1 TU sheep 7. … 8. cow … 9. calf … 10. 10 units of suhur flour 11. 3 units of flour 12. 3 units of … 13. 3 units of cereal 14. 4 metal daggers 15. … animals 16. 10 units of milk 17. 1 unit of cream Reverse Column 1 1. … cow 2. … 3. … ewe 4. 1 stud 5. … 6. … male goat 7. … bird 8. 71 9. a high ranking official 10. a singer 11. a barber 12. a kind of barber 13. … 14. … 15. … 16. acacia 17. cultivation Column 2 1. … 2. … 3. … 4. … 5. a workshop 6. … 7. … 8. … 9. … 10. field work 11. field work 12. overflowing 13. a canal 14. … 15. its wood 16. plow of his workers 17. its reed Column 3 1. … 2. … 3. … 4. its rushes 5. its rushes 6. … 7. … 8. universe 9. … 10. green lapis lazuli 11. thin 12. … 13. … 14. … 15. …; 6 3/16" height x 4 1/4" width x 1" depth, large rectangular multi-column tablet joined from fragments; A mostly complete tablet with an old, poorly-done fill at a corner on one face. One face has considerable cracking. The complete cracks have been filled with an unknown, clear adhesive to prevent the separation of fragments. Numerous cracks radiate out from larger breaks on one face. Many of these cracks are filled with a white accretion material, probably salts, that appear to be causing the cracking and some spalling. The mended breaks are poorly filled, and the fill is shrunken and detaching. In one area there are two small fragments of pinkish-red lint adhered to the surface. (Drawer S3)
- School text, lexical exercise of bird names., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); 31719.4a-b; 1. The arabu bird 2. The UD-sha bird 3. The TAR bird; 3" diameter x 13/16" depth, lentil with an adhesive label attached; This lenticular tablet has broken into two pieces. These two pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. There is a deep loss next to the break near the center of the tablet on the convex, uninscribed face. There are other, shallower surface losses around the break and the deep loss. There are several incomplete cracks overall. There are white concretions visible overall, but are particularly concentrated on the area with losses. There are some shallow gouge marks on the inscribed face that might have been made when the clay was still wet, based on the patina. There is a small, rectangular label adhered to the uninscribed face near the edge with a typed number "4". (Drawer 1)
  This elementary text is a student's vocabulary practice for writing different types of birds.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); SC-I-10; 1. 'She is a lady'; 2. 'She is a lady'; 3. 'The lady of the abzu'; 3 7/16" diameter x 1" depth, baked red color lentil joined from fragments with the reverse inscribed; Lenticular tablet that has broken apart in three pieces. The pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. There are some losses overall, particularly along the breaks and the edges. Gouges in one area at an edge look to have been caused by a modern tool. Another notable loss is a rectangular chunk near the center on the surface of the flat face. There are other incomplete cracks overall on both faces and some spalling on the flat face. (Drawer 2)
  This beginner's exercise is a student's practice writing personal names.
- School text, administrative exercise and mathematical exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-35c; 3" height x 2 1/8" width x 3/4" depth, rectangular single column tablet with transposed writing on the reverse; Rectangular tablet with a few incomplete cracks on one face and some minor spalling on the other face. There is minor damage at two of the corners. One face of the tablet has a dark brown patina with tan clay showing through. The other face is mottled tan, dark brown, and cream-colored. On edge is mostly cream-colored. there are some white concretions visible throughout. (Drawer 3)
  This student tablet contains an administrative exercise for an account on the obverse and a mathematic problem transposed on the reverse
- School text, administrative exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-IV-4; 4 1/4" height x 2" width x 13/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet that has broken into six pieces. these six pieces consist of two main pieces and four other chips from the surface. These pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. The four chips have some jagged edges that extend slightly above the rest of the face, possibly from misalignment while being reattched. Additionally, there are three minor losses: the first is located at one corner, another is near one edge, and the third is near the center on one face. There is a rough patch of a substance, possibly clay (?), along a portion of the break on one face.There are white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 4)
  This student exercise involves female weavers.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 125; 1. 'I saw his strength'; 2. 'I saw her strength'; 3. 'I saw the strength of Ishtar'; 4. (Written by) 'Suen advised'; 2 7/8" diameter x 1 3/4" depth, baked lentil with the obverse destroyed and the reverse inscribed; Lenticular tablet inscribed on only one side. The uninscribed side has depressions and smears that appear to be finger impressions made when the clay was still wet. The inscribed face has a gouge at one edge with some loose fragments in it; these fragments may be at risk for loss. There are hairline cracks in the clay in the area all around the gouge. There are two chips in the edge of the face close to the gouge. One of these chips adjoins a deep crack, part of which goes through to the opposite face. The uninscribed face has a gouge near the edge with two chipped losses adjacent to it. The gouge meets a deep crack that extends across this face and partially goes through to the inscribed face. This face has a few jagged edges from the finger mark (?) depressions. These jagged edges may be at risk for loss. (Drawer 5)
  This elementary student exercise contains unusual personal names. The text is signed by its scribe Ur-Suen.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names beginning with "lu2"., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 47; 2 5/16" diameter x 1/2" depth, baked lentil with the reverse inscribed; Small lenticular tablet with one flattened edge; this edge appears to have been compressed while the clay was still wet. On one face there is a smooth, even loss at one edge that looks like a strike from a modern tool. The outside edge of the tablet is unevenly broken here. On the opposite face, the scrape from the tool is not visible, but the uneven, broken edge is more pronounced. There is a very small, fine crack near the center of this face. The tablet may have been lightly coated with a clear substance. (Drawer 6)
  This basic student exercise is practice writing personal names that begin with "lu2". The reverse is a study on the phonetic values of the names on the obverse.
- School text, mathematical exercise., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); 96502; 3 1/8" height x 1 15/16" width x 3/4" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet with two losses on the face with more cuneiform insciriptions. there is one V-shaped gouge, most likely made with a modern tool. There is another pit-like gouge near one corner. There is a small chip on the other face toward the center of an edge. There is an incomplete crack measuring about 1" running across one edge. There are some white concretions visible overall. (Drawer S2)
  This text is a student practice problem based on a multiplication table for 9.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names beginning with "a"., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-34a; 1. 'The fate of which ones'; 2. 'Sister'; 3. 'Their sister'; 4. 'My sister …'; 5. 'My sister …'; 6. 'My sister …'; 7. 'My sister gave'; 8. …; 9. 'The one above; 10. 'The ones above; 11. 'The one above is my brother'; 6" height x 3 1/2" width x 1 1/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet with an ink mark "BF 22 'A'"; Rectangular tablet of grey-tan clay. There are several losses on the surface. The convex face has a triangular loss near one edge and a linear loss stretching across the center of the face. There is also a sizeable gouge on one edge adjacent to this face that seems to have been made by an implement. It is unclear when this damage was caused. There are also two smaller gouge marks near one corner on this same face. On the same edge as the sizeable gouge, there are circular gouge marks at the center created by an implement. The patina of these is similar to that of the remainder of the tablet indicating these gouge marks are ancient. There are some white concretions visible overall, particularly on the convex face. (Drawer S3)
  This basic student exercise is practice writing personal names that begin with "a". This acrographic arrangment was popular among ancient Mesopotamian vocabularies.
- School text, sign exercise from Syllable Alphabet A., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); 31719.6; (Syllabary--no translation); 2 7/8" diameter x 3/4" depth, lentil with an adhesive label attached; This lenticular tablet has incomplete cracks throughout. There are some gouge marks on the uninscribed face made by a modern tool. There are a few other surface losses along the edge and on the inscribed face. There is a pit-like gouge on the inscirbed face -- it is difficult to tell if this was made while the clay was still wet or after the tablet had dried. There is a small, cream-colored label adhered to the convex face near the edge with an underlined, typed number "6". There is a white substance visible on portions of the surface. There are also some white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 1)
  This beginner's exercise is a practice in sign formation and sound.
- School text, legal exercise of an adoption contract., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-24c; 5 7/8" height x 2 1/4" width x 15/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet that appears to have broken into three pieces. These pieces have been reattached with a clear adhesive. The adhesive is also visible on the surface along some portions of the breaks. There are also some incomplete cracks stemming from these breaks. A portion of one of these cracks is also covered with a clear adhesive. There are some losses along the breaks. Notably, there is one semi-circular chunk lost along one of the breaks near an edge. Three of the corners have minor losses. The fourth corner has a large gouge made with a modern tool. Next to this gouge on one edge is second gouge with a rougher surface. It is unclear if this second gouge was made when the clay was still wet or after the clay had dried. There are some small, white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 2)
  This student practice tablet is an adoption contract. It includes a date that names Rim-Suen, the 10th king of the Larsa dynasty, who reigned from 1822-1763 BCE.